[SLIDE]
Codex CLI Mastery
- 9 modules
- CLI-first workflows
- Safety + quality
[NARRATION]
This training takes you from basic Codex CLI usage to advanced workflows. We focus on safe, repeatable practices that scale from quick fixes to complex systems.
[SLIDE]
Module 1: Getting Started
- Install and authenticate
- First real task
- Safety model
[NARRATION]
Module 1 gets you productive in under an hour. You install Codex CLI, run a real task, and learn the approval and sandbox model that keeps changes safe.
[SLIDE]
What Codex CLI Is
- Works in your repo
- Reads and edits files
- You approve changes
[NARRATION]
Codex CLI is a terminal assistant that operates directly in your codebase. It reads files, proposes edits, and only applies changes after you approve.
[ASSETS]
type: mermaid
purpose: illustrate Codex CLI propose-and-approve loop
content:
flowchart LR
[SLIDE]
Install and Verify
- Install script or npm
- codex auth login
- codex --version
[NARRATION]
Install Codex CLI with the official script or npm, then authenticate with the login flow. Verify the install by checking the version command.
[SLIDE]
First Task Workflow
- Start a session
- Ask a concrete question
- Approve a small edit
[NARRATION]
Begin with a real, scoped task so you learn the feedback loop. Read or summarize files first, then try a tiny edit to see the approval step in action.
[SLIDE]
Safety Model
- Approval modes
- Sandbox modes
- Read-only option
[NARRATION]
Codex uses approvals and sandboxes to prevent unintended changes. Start with suggest or always approvals and use read-only when you only want analysis.
[SLIDE]
Essential Commands
- codex, codex exec
- /diff, /undo
- --sandbox, --profile
[NARRATION]
Learn the core commands early: interactive sessions, non-interactive exec, and the TUI helpers. Profiles and sandbox flags make safety repeatable across projects.
[SLIDE]
Why Skills Matter
- From ad-hoc to process
- Fewer misses
- Faster outcomes
[NARRATION]
Skills shift you from guessing to process. They encode proven workflows, reduce missed steps, and make complex tasks more reliable.
[SLIDE]
Module 2: Skills
- Reusable workflows
- Superpowers library
- Custom skills
[NARRATION]
Module 2 introduces skills as named, repeatable workflows. You learn how to install the library, invoke skills, and build your own.
[SLIDE]
Skills Solve
- Forgotten steps
- Inconsistent prompts
- Trial and error
[NARRATION]
Without skills, people improvise and miss critical steps. Skills provide structure, consistent prompts, and checklists that prevent common mistakes.
[SLIDE]
Install Superpowers
- Clone repo
- Create ~/.codex/skills
- Update AGENTS.md
[NARRATION]
Superpowers is optional but powerful. Clone the library, create a personal skills directory, and configure AGENTS.md to load skills.
[SLIDE]
Bootstrap and Verify
- Run bootstrap
- See skill list
- Update via git pull
[NARRATION]
Run the bootstrap command each session to load skills. Verify that skills are listed, and update the library with a regular git pull.
[SLIDE]
Skill Categories
- Planning
- Quality
- Workflow
[NARRATION]
The core library clusters around planning, quality, and workflow. Each skill defines when to use it, the steps to follow, and anti-patterns to avoid.
[SLIDE]
Invoking Skills
- Explicit call
- Prompt hint
- Ask for suggestion
[NARRATION]
You can call a skill directly, hint it in a prompt, or ask Codex which skill fits. Explicit invocation is the most reliable pattern.
[SLIDE]
Feature Workflow
- Brainstorm
- Plan
- Execute
- Verify
[NARRATION]
A typical skill-driven flow starts with brainstorming to clarify requirements, then a written plan, structured execution, and a verification gate before completion.
[SLIDE]
3-Attempt Rule
- Stop after 3 fails
- Use systematic debugging
- Prevent guess loops
[NARRATION]
After three failed fixes, you are likely guessing. Stop and switch to systematic debugging to trace the root cause and add regression tests.
[ASSETS]
type: mermaid
purpose: show 3-attempt rule decision path
content:
flowchart TD
[SLIDE]
Skill Anti-Patterns
- Skipping steps
- Guessing after 3 tries
- Declaring done early
[NARRATION]
Common failures come from skipping steps or declaring completion without verification. Skills exist to prevent these shortcuts.
[SLIDE]
Build Custom Skills
- Repeatable workflows
- Steps + checklists
- Team consistency
[NARRATION]
Create a custom skill when you repeat the same workflow. A template with steps, checklists, and anti-patterns makes team practices consistent.
[SLIDE]
Module 3: Speed and Efficiency
- Batch operations
- Prompt pipelines
- Context control
[NARRATION]
Module 3 focuses on efficiency. You learn to batch independent work, chain prompts effectively, and preserve context without wasting tokens.
[SLIDE]
Batching Requests
- Read many files at once
- Combine tool actions
- Fewer round trips
[NARRATION]
When tasks are independent, bundle them in one request. This reduces latency, keeps context tighter, and speeds up decisions.
[SLIDE]
Prompt Pipelines
- Discovery to plan to execute
- Sequential prompt orchestration
- Parallel terminals OK
[NARRATION]
In practice, you orchestrate work as a sequence of prompts and hand-offs. Use separate terminals or codex exec for parallel investigations.
[SLIDE]
Context Optimization
- Targeted reads
- Summaries under 500 tokens
- Resume or manual context files
[NARRATION]
Keep prompts scoped and reuse short summaries. When running parallel sessions, persist context in files to avoid losing critical decisions.
[SLIDE]
Task Decomposition
- Dependency-first
- Role templates
- Verification chains
[NARRATION]
Decompose by dependencies so independent reads happen together. Role-based prompts and verification chains keep execution orderly and testable.
[SLIDE]
Verification Chains
- Summarize change
- Ask for tests
- Run and confirm
[NARRATION]
After a change, summarize what changed, ask what should be tested, run those tests, and only proceed on a clean result.
[SLIDE]
Strategy Selection
- Batch, pipeline, or single prompt
- Choose by dependency
- Always validate
[NARRATION]
Pick the execution strategy that matches the dependency structure. Regardless of the path, finish with a validation step.
[SLIDE]
Module 4: Planning
- Prevent scope creep
- Stage execution
- Handle ambiguity
[NARRATION]
Module 4 focuses on planning and execution. You learn how to structure plans, execute in batches, and clarify ambiguous requirements.
[SLIDE]
Why Plan
- Avoid rework
- Surface edge cases
- Track progress
[NARRATION]
Planning avoids mid-stream refactors and missed requirements. It also gives you a clear progress signal as you complete stages.
[SLIDE]
Plan Structure
- Stages with goals
- Success criteria
- Tests + files
[NARRATION]
A good plan breaks work into stages, each with goals and success criteria. It lists tests to write and files to touch.
[SLIDE]
Plan-Review-Execute
- Plan first
- Review checkpoints
- Execute in stages
[NARRATION]
Use a plan-review-execute loop to keep control. Review after each stage so problems are caught early.
[ASSETS]
type: mermaid
purpose: show plan-review-execute cycle
content:
flowchart LR
[SLIDE]
Batch Execution
- Small batches
- Test per batch
- Commit per stage
[NARRATION]
Batching reduces risk. Keep batches small, test after each batch, and commit changes stage by stage.
[SLIDE]
Handling Ambiguity
- Ask focused options
- Update plan
- Resume execution
[NARRATION]
When requirements are unclear, pause to clarify options. Update the plan, then proceed with the chosen direction.
[SLIDE]
Module 5: Quality
- Multi-layer review
- TDD + debugging
- Quality gates
[NARRATION]
Module 5 builds quality into every step. You apply layered reviews, test-driven development, and strong verification gates.
[SLIDE]
Multi-Layer Review
- Automated checks
- AI review
- Human review
[NARRATION]
Each review layer catches different defects. Combining automated checks, AI review, and human review raises reliability.
[ASSETS]
type: mermaid
purpose: illustrate multi-layer review flow
content:
flowchart LR
[SLIDE]
TDD with Codex
- Red to green to refactor
- Tests first
- Minimal code
[NARRATION]
Use Codex as a pair programmer for TDD. Write the failing test first, implement the smallest fix, then refactor safely.
[SLIDE]
Systematic Debugging
- Reproduce
- Trace root cause
- Hypothesize and verify
[NARRATION]
Stop guessing and debug systematically. Reproduce the issue, trace the root cause, form a hypothesis, and verify with a regression test.
[SLIDE]
Quality Gates
- Verification before completion
- Lint, test, typecheck
- No silent failures
[NARRATION]
Quality gates are explicit checkpoints before claiming done. Run tests, linting, and type checks, and fix failures immediately.
[SLIDE]
Root Cause Analysis
- Trace backwards
- Identify trigger
- Prevent recurrence
[NARRATION]
Root cause analysis focuses on the original trigger, not the surface symptom. Capture the cause, then prevent it with tests or validation.
[SLIDE]
Quality Takeaways
- Layered reviews
- TDD discipline
- Verification habit
[NARRATION]
The quality discipline is about consistency. Layered reviews, test-first habits, and verification gates compound over time.
[SLIDE]
Module 6: Domain Work
- Refactoring
- Architecture exploration
- Security + performance
[NARRATION]
Module 6 covers deeper domain work. You learn safe refactoring, system exploration, performance tuning, and security reviews.
[SLIDE]
Large Refactors
- Interface first
- Extract by provider
- Clean up last
[NARRATION]
Refactor large codebases by creating interfaces and isolating providers. This keeps changes safe and reversible.
[SLIDE]
Architecture Exploration
- Entry points
- Key flows
- Dependencies map
[NARRATION]
Start by mapping entry points and primary flows. Then identify dependencies and data flow to understand the system quickly.
[SLIDE]
Legacy Code Changes
- Characterization tests
- Find a seam
- Change safely
[NARRATION]
For legacy code, capture current behavior with characterization tests, find a seam for isolation, and make changes safely.
[SLIDE]
Performance Optimization
- Measure first
- Analyze bottlenecks
- Validate gains
[NARRATION]
Optimization starts with measurement. Analyze the bottleneck, optimize cautiously, and validate results with before-after data.
[SLIDE]
Security Review
- Input validation
- Auth checks
- Sensitive data
[NARRATION]
Security reviews focus on validation, authentication boundaries, and sensitive data handling. Build checklists so issues are caught consistently.
[SLIDE]
Module 7: Integration
- GitHub CLI
- Multi-tool workflows
- CI/CD
[NARRATION]
Module 7 integrates Codex into real workflows. You use GitHub CLI, orchestrate multiple tools, and connect to CI pipelines.
[SLIDE]
GitHub CLI
- PRs, issues, checks
- Fewer browser hops
- Faster reviews
[NARRATION]
The gh CLI lets Codex manage pull requests and issues directly. It reduces context switching and speeds up review loops.
[SLIDE]
Multi-Tool Workflows
- Combine scripts + gh
- Single prompt orchestration
- Structured outputs
[NARRATION]
Design workflows that combine scripts, gh, and Codex prompts. Use structured outputs so Codex can synthesize results.
[SLIDE]
CI/CD Integration
- Trigger checks
- Diagnose failures
- Rerun safely
[NARRATION]
Codex can watch CI runs, summarize failures, and help rerun jobs. This tight loop reduces time to fix broken builds.
[SLIDE]
Knowledge Transfer
- Playbooks and patterns
- Prompt templates
- Share workflows
[NARRATION]
Make knowledge portable by capturing workflows in playbooks and templates. This prevents tribal knowledge and speeds onboarding.
[SLIDE]
Module 8: API Internals
- Session architecture
- Tool wrappers
- Context control
[NARRATION]
Module 8 dives into how Codex sessions work internally. You learn how tools are invoked and how to manage context safely.
[SLIDE]
Session Architecture
- Prompt in, tools out
- Approvals enforced
- Deterministic flow
[NARRATION]
A session takes a prompt, calls tools as needed, and applies changes only with approval. Understanding the flow helps you design safer automations.
[SLIDE]
Tool Wrappers
- Define helpers
- JSON schemas
- Structured results
[NARRATION]
Tool wrappers let Codex call your scripts. Define a clear schema and return structured JSON so outputs are easy to combine.
[SLIDE]
Context and Tokens
- Summaries over raw logs
- Persist key state
- Avoid duplication
[NARRATION]
Manage the context budget by summarizing outputs and persisting only what you need. This keeps sessions stable and efficient.
[SLIDE]
Chaining Requests
- Discovery to plan to execute
- Local scripts for data
- Explicit hand-offs
[NARRATION]
Complex work is best handled by chained prompts. Use local scripts to gather data, then pass explicit hand-offs between stages.
[SLIDE]
Module 9: Customization
- Project rules
- Permissions
- Automation
[NARRATION]
Module 9 shows how to customize Codex for your project. You define instructions, set permissions, and automate routine checks.
[SLIDE]
AGENTS.md
- Project overview
- Conventions
- Guardrails
[NARRATION]
AGENTS.md is where you define project context and rules. Clear instructions guide Codex toward safe and consistent behavior.
[SLIDE]
Config and Permissions
- Approval modes
- Sandbox scopes
- Profiles
[NARRATION]
Set approval and sandbox policies based on risk. Profiles make it easy to switch between safe analysis and trusted automation.
[SLIDE]
Automation Hooks
- Git hooks
- CI checks
- Repeatable gates
[NARRATION]
Automation hooks enforce quality by default. Use git hooks and CI to prevent regressions before code reaches main.
[SLIDE]
MCP Servers
- External resources
- Structured context
- Safe integration
[NARRATION]
MCP servers provide structured resources like schemas or files. They allow Codex to pull context safely without ad-hoc scraping.
[SLIDE]
Wrap-Up
- Practice modules in order
- Use skills early
- Verify every change
[NARRATION]
Progress through the modules in sequence and apply skills early. The consistent theme is safety and verification on every change.